Since 2003, a special type of scam targeting the elderly
Od roku 2003 w Japonii króluje biorące na cel osoby starsze
called the money transfer scam has proliferated in Japan.
oszustwo zwane „przekrętem na przelew”.
Financial damages increased every year, reaching 56.5 billion yen in 2014.
Straty finansowe rosną z roku na rok. W 2014 r. wynosiły 56,5 miliarda jenów.
Now, in 2019, scammers have changed their techniques,
W 2019 roku oszuści zmienili metody,
and the damage continues.
w dalszym ciągu okradając obywateli.
-Are you saying my men are involved? -Yes.
- Sugeruje pan, że to moi ludzie? - Tak.
This guy is a reliable and seasoned professional.
To niezawodny, doświadczony zawodowiec.
And as soon as he does a job for you, he gets jumped?
Pracował dla ciebie i od razu go napadli?
We were robbed as soon as we used a new collector,
Okradli nas, gdy wzięliśmy nowego kuriera,
casting the shadow of a doubt over you.
to może być wasza sprawka.
Kanbe...
Kanbe.
do you really want to mess with me?
Naprawdę chcesz ze mną zadzierać?
Do you want a war?
Chcesz wojny?
Go get him! Now!
Brać go! Już!
Give me a freakin' break!
Dajcie spokój!
Dokugawa-san, what did Kurusu do?
Panie Dokugawa, co on zrobił?
That punk was working with the robbers!
Ten śmieć współpracował ze złodziejami!
Go after him! You stay here! Hurry!
Za nim! A ty tu zostań! Już!
What's your job? You're the leader. Show some dignity!
Jesteś ich szefem. Miejże godność!
Bring me my nine million yen!
Przynieś mi moje dziewięć milionów!
When things go wrong, shouldn't the financiers share the loss?
Inwestorzy nie powinni pokryć części strat?
Nine million yen by this weekend.
Dziewięć baniek do weekendu.
-Hurry up! -What happened to Shiro?
- Szybko! - Co z Shirem?
I don't give a damn about him!
Mam go w dupie!
They'll be here in no time! Hurry!
Zaraz nas dorwą!
Is this the Kurusu home?
Jest tu pan Kurusu?
What makes you think anyone lives here?
Czy to ci wygląda na czyjś dom?
Maybe he's here to redeliver a package we missed.
Może chce nam dostarczyć przesyłkę.
Oh, yeah. They do that in the city!
W mieście tak robią.
-That's definitely it. -For sure!
- Na pewno. - Jasne.
You're not a delivery man!
Nie jesteś kurierem!
Then what's he here for?
To czego tu szuka?
I don't know.
Nie wiem.
It hurts!
To boli!
Dokugawa-san?
Panie Dokugawa.
Yes.
Tak.
I took care of it.
Zająłem się tym.
Got it.
Oczywiście.
EPISODE 8
ODCINEK 8
I didn't tell you,
Nie mówiłem ci,
but we were robbed a while back.
ale niedawno nas okradli.
Our financiers suspected us, so we set a trap.
Inwestorzy podejrzewali nas, więc zastawiliśmy pułapkę.
Soon after that, we caught one of the crooks.
Złapaliśmy jednego ze złodziei.
We roughed him up, then he named--
Wskazał imię.
Kurusu.
Kurusu.
I won't forgive him.
Nie wybaczę mu.
Where is Kurusu?
Gdzie Kurusu?
He ran away.
Uciekł.
What?
Co?
-What are you doing? -What do you mean?
- Co ty tu robisz? - W sensie?
I was waiting for you.
Czekałem na pana.
You were waiting for... what?
Niby na co?
Go find him!
Leć za nim!
We're paying you a lot for this!
Słono ci za to płacimy!
-You're giving me less than market price-- -Go!
- Nie dostaję nawet średniej... - Ruchy!
Go! Go after him! Run!
Znajdź go! Już!
I said run!
Biegiem!
Hey, I heard from that Shiro guy
Shiro mówił,
that you were the ones who were robbing those old folks' homes.
że włamania to wasza sprawka.
Were you working with anyone else?
Był z wami jeszcze ktoś?
Tell me!
Gadaj!
If you want to know...
Jeśli chcesz wiedzieć,
-then stop kicking me-- -What?
- przestań mnie kopać... - Co?
-Let's make a deal!
- Dobijmy targu!
Smart thinking, Toki!
Dobrze kombinujesz!
Beat him in a battle of wits!
Pokonaj go sprytem!
A battle of wits?
Sprytem?
You must be a pretty smart guy!
Pewnie spryciarz z ciebie.
I'll do this until you talk!
Będę tak robił, aż mi powiecie.
I'll talk!
Wszystko powiem!
Seimiya!
Seimiya!
-What? -We worked with a guy called Seimiya!
- Co? - Pomagał nam Seimiya.
Hello. It's Mori.
Mówi Mori.
Yes, we just got back.
Właśnie wróciliśmy.
Seimiya?
Seimiya?
Don't say his name!
Nie mów tego na głos!
We're headed back there now, so keep an eye on him.
Wracamy, miej go na oku.
-Got it? -Yes.
- Rozumiesz? - Tak.
-But... -What?
- Ale... - Co?
Well... Seimiya is...
Jego tu...
not here.
nie ma.
What?
Co?
Find him, you idiot!
Znajdź go, kretynie!
Kusano!
Kusano!
Are you working with Seimiya?
Pomagałeś Seimiyi?
Of course not.
Skądże.
I know you were meeting secretly!
Wiem, że się spotykaliście!
You thought you were being so sneaky, huh?
Takie z was podstępne cwaniaki?
We were just drinking together.
Tylko piliśmy.
I had nothing to do with the robberies.
Nie mam nic wspólnego z włamaniami.
So what about your secret register?
A wasz tajny rejestr?
-How did you know? -So it's true. Your profits were too good.
- Skąd pan wie? - Więc to prawda. Za dużo zarabialiście.
I was bluffing.
Blefowałem.
I'll hear all about it after we're done with this.
Opowiesz mi, jak skończymy.
Don't even think about running away.
Ani mi się waż wiać.
There!
Tam!
Here? Which room?
Gdzie? Który pokój?
-201! -Got it!
- Numer 201! - Jasne!
He came back and packed his things.
Wrócił i się spakował.
He should still be close by.
Nie uciekł daleko.
-Let's go! -Okay.
- Szybciej! - Jasne.
Shit!
Cholera!
Why won't you pick up?
Czemu nie odbierasz?
Pick up!
Odbierz!
Shit!
Cholera.
Kusano...
Kusano...
What did you do?
Coś ty zrobił?
-What did you do? -It's not what you think!
- Co narobiłeś? - To nie tak!
Shut up! You're coming with me.
Stul dziób. Idziemy.
No! They'll kill me!
Nie! Zabiją mnie.
They suspect me now, too.
Mnie też podejrzewają.
I didn't mean for this to happen!
Nie chciałem tego!
I told you I borrowed a lot of money a long time ago, right?
Mówiłem ci, że mam długi.
I was hiding from them, but they finally found me!
Ukrywałem się, ale mnie znaleźli.
They told me if I didn't pay it back right away,
Zagrozili, że jeśli nie oddam forsy,
they'd go after my family!
dorwą moją rodzinę.
I had to do something!
Musiałem coś zrobić!
I was desperate!
Nie miałem wyjścia!
I could've paid it back with the money from scamming,
Zarobiłbym na przekrętach,
but then you said you'd quit!
ale postanowiłeś odejść.
I didn't think I could keep going without you!
Bez ciebie nie dałbym rady.
So I panicked,
Spanikowałem,
and I knew one of the guys who was collecting money for us.
a znam jednego z kurierów.
And so...
No i...
-So you organized the robbery? -That's right!
- Zorganizowałeś to? - Tak!
I told Kurusu I needed help.
Powiedziałem Kurusu, że mam kłopoty.
Why?
Dlaczego?
Why didn't you say anything to me?
Dlaczego nie mnie?
How could I?
A jak?
You said you wanted to go back to having a normal life.
Chciałeś wrócić do normalnego życia.
I didn't want to trouble you!
Nie chciałem ci sprawiać kłopotu!
There he is! Seimiya!
Tam jest! Seimiya!
You bastard!
Draniu!
What did you do?
Coś ty narobił?
Hey! Stop!
Nie! Dość!
Get off of me!
Przestań!
Hey!
Ej!
Stop!
Stój!
I'm sorry! Forgive me!
Przepraszam! Wybacz mi!
Please! Please!
Błagam!
I'm sorry!
Przepraszam!
Please! I don't want to die!
Nie chcę umierać!
Let me see them one more time!
Pozwól mi ich jeszcze zobaczyć!
I'm a terrible person!
Jestem okropny.
There's so much I want to apologize for!
Chcę przeprosić za tyle rzeczy!
Please, I'll do anything!
Zrobię wszystko!
I'll do anything!
Wszystko!
Dokugawa called me.
Dzwonił Dokugawa.
He said they got Kurusu.
Znaleźli Kurusu.
What... will happen to us?
A co z nami?
We're meeting with the financiers tomorrow.
Jutro mamy spotkanie z inwestorami.
It won't be good.
Będzie ciężko.
Also...
A poza tym...
I heard you were hiding something from us, Kusano.
Ponoć coś przed nami ukrywałeś, Kusano.
I already threw the register away.
Wyrzuciłem już rejestr.
You have the original data, right?
Ale masz dane źródłowe, prawda?
We'll give it to our higher-ups as an apology.
Damy je szefostwu w ramach przeprosin.
I just sent someone to your house.
Mój człowiek je przyniesie.
My house?
Ode mnie?
-Wait, I can bring-- -It's too late!
- Sam je... - Za późno!
Our reputation has been completely ruined.
Nasza reputacja legła w gruzach.
Tojo is going to cut off one or both of my arms for this.
Tojo odrąbie mi za to rękę. Albo obie.
The debt we owe is worth more than both of your lives.
Jesteśmy im winni więcej, niż jesteśmy warci.
It's too late.
Już za późno.
It's too late for all of us!
Dla nas wszystkich!
Kanbe-san!
Panie Kanbe.
Kusano had nothing to do with this!
Kusano nic o tym nie wiedział!
I did it all myself! He had no idea!
Ja za tym stałem! On nie!
It's all my fault!
To moja wina!
It's my fault!
Moja!
So please spare him!
Proszę go oszczędzić!
Please!
Błagam!
Dokugawa and I...
Ja i Dokugawa...
were players just like you guys once.
też byliśmy kiedyś tacy jak wy.
We planned to make money and quit right away,
Chcieliśmy się nachapać i odejść,
but it just kept dragging on.
ale nas to pochłonęło.
Get lost.
Spadajcie.
Go.
Już.
We should be safe now.
Jesteśmy bezpieczni.
Kusano...
Kusano...
what are you going to do?
co teraz zrobisz?
I need to go home.
Wrócę do domu.
Will you be okay on your own?
Poradzisz sobie sam?
Yeah.
Tak.
You should go to your family, too.
Ty też jedź do rodziny.
I bet they've been waiting a long time.
Dość już się naczekali.
Be careful.
Uważaj na siebie.
You, too.
Ty też.
Here we are.
Jesteśmy.
-Thanks a lot, Misaki-chan. -My pleasure.
- Dziękuję, Misaki. - Nie ma sprawy.
-I'll make some tea. -Okay.
- Zrobię herbatę. - Dobrze.
I wonder if Makoto's home.
Ciekawe, czy Makoto już wrócił.
-The lights were on in his room. -Were they?
- Światło się u niego paliło. - Tak?
Makoto?
Makoto?
We're home!
Jesteśmy!
Take that laptop.
Weź laptop.
What are you...
Co wy...
Give that back!
Oddawaj to!
Give it back!
Oddawaj!
-Give it back! -Hand it over, old lady!
- Oddaj to! - Puszczaj, paniusiu!
Wait! Don't hurt her!
Nie krzywdź jej!
Stop!
Przestań!
Stop it!
Dość!
Why are you stopping me? Get off!
Co robisz? Puszczaj!
-Sorry! -Misaki-chan!
- Wybacz! - Misaki!
-Take this! -Hey! Get out of my way!
- Weź to! - Z drogi!
Gouriki!
Gouriki!
Gouriki, wait!
Zaczekaj!
I said wait!
Stój!
What are you doing?
Co ty wyprawiasz?
We were only there for the laptop!
Mieliśmy tylko zabrać laptop!
We have our orders.
Mamy rozkazy.
We can't hurt them!
Nie możemy ich skrzywdzić.
Then you just sit on your ass forever!
To siedź na dupie!
Grandma! Grandma!
Babciu!
Quick, hide! Anywhere!
Schowaj się gdzieś!
-Hurry! -What's wrong?
- Szybko! - Co się dzieje?
What?
No co?
-What are you-- -Give it to me!
- Co ty... - Oddawaj to!
What are you doing?
Co ty wyprawiasz?
-Stop! -Give it!
- Nie! - Oddawaj!
-Hand it over! -No!
- Daj to! - Nie!
What are you doing?
Co ty robisz?
Give it to me now!
Dawaj, ale już!
-No! -Let go!
- Nie! - Puszczaj!
-Let me go! -Give it to me!
- Zostaw mnie! - Oddaj!
Stop!
Przestań!
Take that!
A masz!
Bastard!
Draniu!
Screw you!
Wal się!
Excuse me.
Przepraszam.
Kusano-san?
Pan Kusano?
-Hey, Kusano! -Hey!
- Kusano! - Stój!
Kanbe-san!
Panie Kanbe!
Thank God!
Całe szczęście.
They didn't cut off your hands or legs.
Ma pan ręce i nogi.
You even have your fingers.
I nawet palce.
Yeah.
Tak.
But in return,
Ale w zamian
they want 80% of our earnings for the next three years.
żądają 80% dochodów przez trzy lata.
What?
Co?
We have no choice.
Nie mamy wyboru.
All of this...
To wszystko...
is my fault.
moja wina.
Want to go to the beach?
Skoczymy na plażę?
What?
Co?
The beach.
Na plażę.
-I'd love to. -Yeah.
- Chętnie. - Super.
It's been a while.
Kopę lat.
Guess who?
Poznajesz?
Any idea?
Zgaduj.
I'm looking at you right now.
Właśnie na ciebie patrzę.
I'm over here. No, the other way! To your left!
Tu jestem. Z lewej!
That's right, turn to your left. Just a little more.
Właśnie, z lewej. Jeszcze odrobina.
Subtitle translation by Marti McElreath
Napisy: Konrad Szabowicz